Guide to the Dr. George C.Y. Chiou ophthalmology career publications and papers, 1979-2019 MS 852
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Dr. George C.Y. Chiou ophthalmology career publications and papers
1979-2019
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Chiou, George C. Y.
MS 852
0.25 Linear Feet 1 box
The collection consists of records, news coverage, and materials from the career of Regents Professor Emeritus Dr. George C. Y. Chiou.
Biographical / Historical
Dr. George C. Y. Chiou was born in Taoyuan, Taiwan in 1934, and after earning B.S. and M.S. degrees at National Taiwan University, in 1964 he emigrated to the U. S. to pursue a doctoral degree in pharmacology at Vanderbilt University. His wife and two daughters remained in Taiwan for a year and a half but then joined him in Nashville. On completion of his doctoral degree, in 1969 he was hired by the medical school of the University of Florida as assistant professor of pharmacology. Then in 1978 Dr. Chiou was hired away from the University of Florida Medical School to be head of the Department of Medical Pharmacology at the Texas A & M University School of Medicine Health Science Center. To his teaching and research he added administrative duties, serving as assistant dean in 1985-86 and associate dean 1987 to 1990.
The focus of Dr. Chiou's research has been the development of new drugs for eye diseases. It has resulted in approximately thirty patents and has been recognized with awards such as the 2006 Excellence in Research Award by the College of Medicine, Texas A & M Health Science Center and the 2007 Patent and Innovation Award by the Office of Technology Communication, Texas A & M System. The first of the treatments developed by Dr. Chiou was the use of D-timolol to treat glaucoma. Developing eyedrops for the delivery of insulin was another achievement, and it was followed by discovery of a drug compound, MC-1101, that can potentially treat and halt the progression of dry age-related macular degeneration. Dr. Chiou has had the support of the Texas A & M Office of Technology Commercialization to bring this product to market. The name of the resulting company is MacuCLEAR.
The bibliography of Dr. Chiou's authored and co-authored papers includes 265 items. He was the founding editor of the Journal of Ocular Pharmacology and Therapeutics, of which the 2004 volume is the twentieth. He was also the editor of two editions of Ophthalmic Toxicology, a book intended for a wide variety of readers in academia, industry, clinics, research laboratories, and government agencies.
In addition to his position in the College of Medicine at Texas A & M, between 1986 and 1995 Dr. Chiou also held adjunct professorships in the Center for Biotechnology and the Department of Ophthalmology at Baylor College of Medicine in Houston. In recognition of his accomplishments, in 2011 he was promoted to Regents Professor in the Department of Neuroscience and Experimental Therapeutics of the College of Medicine at Texas A & M, and in 2015 he became Regents Professor Emeritus.
Content Description
The collection consists of records, news coverage, and materials from the career of Regents Professor Emeritus Dr. George C. Y. Chiou. It includes a plaque on which is mounted a cover of the Journal of Ocular Pharmacology, Dr. Chiou having been the founding editor. There are also three bound volumes: the second edition of Ophthalmic Toxicology, edited by Dr. Chiou (1999); volume 20 of the Journal of Ocular Pharmacology and Therapeutics (2004); and The Vision of Innovation, The Challenge [sic] Story of New Drug Inventor and Entrepreneur George C. Y. Chiou (written in Chinese)(2015).
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Dr. George C.Y. Chiou via the Chao Center for Asian Studies, in April 2019.
Related Materials
Chiou, George, interview by Li, Priscilla and Clark, Zoe. April 05, 2019. Houston Asian American Archives oral history interviews, MS 573, Woodson Research Center, Fondren Library, Rice University. http://hdl.handle.net/1911/106046.
Index Terms
Subjects
History; Medicine; Asian Americans; Health care and medicine
Document Types
clippings (information artifacts); awards; publications
- Series I: Vitae, news coverage, and award
  - Curriculum vitae, updated 7/2019 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - News coverage of MacuCLEAR, 2002-2019 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - News coverage of career awards, 1982-1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - News coverage of eye drops for delivery of insulin, 1988-1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - News coverage of D-timolol to treat glaucoma, 1979-1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II: Publications
  - Journal of Ocular Pharmacology and Therapeutics, Vol. 20, 2004 (Box 1, Folder -)
  - Ophthalmic Toxicology, second edition, George C. Y. Chiou, editor (Box 1, Folder -)
  - The Vision of Innovation, The Challenge [sic] Story of New Drug Inventor and Entrepreneur George C. Y. Chiou (Box 1, Folder -)